So the first and older and actually very successful and impactful way of doing AI-assisted theorem proving is Sledgehammer, so-called Sledgehammer.
So Sledgehammer was developed in 2010 by Larry Paulson and Jasmin Blanchette, both are two of the core Isabelle developers in 2010.
And it basically bridges interactive theorem provers like Isabelle with external automated theorem provers.
So these are called SMT solvers for instance, so first order logic solvers.
I mean, we don't even need to go into what type of external theorem provers are used.
It's all what you need to know is really the general architecture.
So what happens here is that we have a goal that we want to prove in Isabelle.
And the system, the Sledgehammer, the way it works is that it selects some existing facts using a basic machine learning filter.
So that, for example, if you want to prove something about lists, if you want to prove something about filters on lists,
then it chooses all the lemmas that are relevant that seem related to filters on lists.
So lemmas that take filter and lemmas that take maybe concatenation and filter and mapping and filter and so forth.
So that's the first step.
And then after it gets all those theorems, all those facts about lists and filters or the relevant facts,
it moves, it passes them along with the goal that you want to prove to an external automated theorem prover, ATP.
And that external theorem prover will try to prove your goal using the facts that were selected by this machine learning based filter.
And then afterwards, after the fact, after the external theorem prover finish, if it is successful,
it gives you, okay, this is my proof. And these are actually the lemmas that I needed.
I didn't need all the facts that you filtered. I only needed some minimal lemmas.
And then the proof from that external theorem prover is again reconstructed inside Isabelle,
because Isabelle actually does not trust external theorem provers because they might have bugs in them.
So what we do, so basically the process is you want to prove an Isabelle sub-goal, use Sledgehammer.
How does Sledgehammer work? Use machine learning to set up some facts that seem relevant to proving this goal,
then sends those facts along with the goal to an external theorem prover.
And then if the external theorem prover succeeds, we take its proof and try to redo it again inside Isabelle
so that it becomes an Isabelle proof rather than external theorem prover's proof.
And this approach really has a great advantage, which is that it blends the best of both worlds.
So you have the efficiency of all these external theorem provers, which could solve goals
that cannot be solved by O2 or fast-force or same for any of the internal methods.
But at the same time, you still have the trustworthiness of Isabelle's kernel.
And I will just do a very short demo for you as to how to use Sledgehammer to prove a goal.